howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
jimrudshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
today's guest is robin hansen robin's a
regular on the show i think this is his
fourth appearance
uh in his day job robin is a professor
of economics at george mason university
he's described his mission modestly as a
sacred
quest to understand everything and to
save the world
pretty cool i like that i mean look at
my progress and how long i'm likely to
live i'm not really sure that uh
that's really on target but we're going
to keep trying we're going to keep shots
all we can do right
he writes an amazingly interesting blog
at overcomingbias.com and his tweet
stream at robin hansen
is well worth following today's topic
is do we live in a simulation
a topic that i remember uh discussing in
a
freshman session at mit in 1971
so people have been thinking about this
for a long time uh
and robin's been thinking about it for
in a formal sense for longer than most
before we jump into it i'm going to
stipulate at least and i'll actually
let you know robin can push back on this
if he wants i'm going to stipulate that
there are limits
to this kind of speculation about the
ground of being
that we're going to get engage in today
for example
we can't disprove the assertion that the
universe was created five
seconds ago with all of our memories in
place and all ballistic
objects in motion so there are serious
bounds to metaphysical speculations of
all sorts
but with that let's hop in i got a
degree in philosophy of science a long
time ago so i think i'm real
and i you know i did ai where it which
is a lot of you know how you do
reasoning and thinking and after all
that background i'm relatively skeptical
of the value of sort of introducing
these fundamental limits on what you
could know arguments
seems to me you just dive into a topic
and you figure out what you can say and
what you can't
temporarily at least and and that's what
you should do
uh trying to draw some grand law about
topics you should not
go into because you couldn't possibly
know that just doesn't seem to work for
me
yeah i agree i said we're going to live
in the actual world uh the fact that we
can't
disprove you know logical impossibility
of x you know
flying spaghetti monsters or the
universe was created five seconds ago
uh you know it can't constrain us
otherwise we'd starve to death right
that's the
reality of a pragmatic being in the
universe is
hey we make decisions we have ideas
etc so back to the topic of do we live
in a simulation the earliest thing i
found from you in writing at least was a
paper uh back in june of 2001 which i
believe was
prior to bostrom's speculations the very
interesting and in some ways humorous uh
paper called how to live in a simulation
uh was that the start of your thinking
or have you been thinking about this for
longer
i had been on mailing lists which had
discussed the topic for the previous
10 years ad hadn't as had nick bostrom
i mean he didn't get that out of his own
head i mean that was also an idea that
was
lots of people had been talking about
for a while in the mailing list that we
shared
and you know i was responding in part to
people talking about a lot but
i find it interesting that for odd
hypotheses like this
there's vastly more interest in the
question is it true
than how does it matter
so even like are there aliens or other
sort of dramatic hypotheses
overwhelmingly people will talk about is
it true
and they rarely get around to talking
about how does it matter if it matters
uh so my paper was there on the how does
it matter if it matters topic
and it seemed to me that that was
neglected so i was able you know in a
relatively short time to come up with a
bunch of obvious conclusions about how
it would matter
and that would affect what you would do
if you believed you lived in the
stipulation similarly you could write
other analyses on
what the consequences are if there are
aliens or if we'll be able to
do brain emulations in the future or if
there were
you know long ago advanced civilizations
that died down that we
you know don't yet know about all these
topics
i find it interesting that people have
an overwhelming interest
in talking about is it true and you get
to
okay if it were true how would it matter
people lose interest
it's interesting and yeah you came up
with a quite snappy
uh uh argument on what you should do if
we do live in a simulation in fact i'm
going to read the quote
back from your paper which i just
thought was hilariously
rich and good and i don't know quite
what to make of it but i'd love to get
your thoughts on it
if you might be living in a similar
simulation then all
else equal you should care less about
others
live more for today make your world look
more likely to become rich
expect to and try more to participate in
pivotal events
be more entertaining and praiseworthy
and keep the famous people around you
happier and more interested
in you i just love that i'm not quite
sure why
but it's just very interesting
well i would say it is sort of the
logical implications of the hypothesis
and what might be funny is that you
usually expect
advice people give to fit the usual
tropes of
you know admirable living usually
whatever arguments you give are supposed
to draw the conclusion
that we should love each other and be
more communal and
think about the long run and care for
our children and
you know love art you know in some sense
that's the generic
conclusion of every argument about what
you should do because we all just expect
people to be trying to argue for that so
it's often funny to see
when you go through an analysis you draw
conclusions that aren't those
conclusions
although interestingly in this case the
conclusion looks very much like the way
people actually live
well yeah people aren't that crazy but
yeah so it pushes you even more in that
direction relative to the ideals you
might
typically espouse anyway that was a very
good introduction people can
can check that out on robin's essay
which as usual will have on the episode
page
so let's uh start with the probably the
framing that
is most talked about though i'm going to
explain why i think bostrom's
view of ancestor simulation is limited
later
but maybe you can lay out his three-part
argument a little bit and
your take on that well sure so um
there's three scenarios uh he says and
that they're the only options and you
have to pick between one of the three
so um one scenario is that
as we move on into the future uh we will
never
really be able to uh create
simulations that is we'll never get the
capability
the technology or maybe we'll even die
out and we'll just never
be able to create creatures who are
living in a simulation and don't really
know that that's the fact
it requires some technical abilities to
do that you have to be able to create
these
simulated creatures who have a rich life
and who
think you know a lot like a human like
us thinks and feels
and um i have a whole book on how uh you
know what would happen if that
technology were to become widespread
called the age of m but basically one
scenario says
that doesn't happen we never are able to
make these future creatures
a second scenario says we do become able
to make these future creatures
and we do even make a few but we don't
make very many
for some reason uh when the future is
able to make
creatures like us who could be fooled
into thinking they were living in a
simulation
uh there is the potential that they
could make a lot of them
an enormous number but they don't they
just make a few
and the third scenario is that the
future is able to make these creatures
like us
and that they do make
creatures like us and they make a lot of
creatures like us
and therefore there are more of those
creatures in the future
who think they are living in a world
like us than there are actually people
living in the time and you know manner
that we think we live
and if that's true then if you ask well
which of them am i you have to conclude
you're more likely to be one of those
future creatures than one of the current
creatures who thinks
you're in the real world most people who
think they're
living in our era and in our time are
wrong
most of them are creatures in the future
who believe
that this is what they're living and the
claim is
you have to pick one of these three
scenarios now obviously there could be
other reasons why you might be living in
a simulation you might be in some other
you know very different universe which
creates a creature like you but that
just adds to the possibility that you
might be living in a simulation
so the claim is you've got to pick one
of these three options
i pick the option that they don't care
much
so i agree that most likely the future
will be able to create simulations like
us
most likely they will create some of
them and
um you know that will be important but
when i look
from our era back and i say the
analogies
of what we do to make things that are
like simulations of our ancestors we
make movies we make plays we write
novels we play
games or video games and when we
try to simulate our ancestors and sort
of
you know do as best we can with that our
interest
fades much more quickly than does
population
so you know before 200 years ago
basically
population doubled every thousand years
but it seems to me our interest in the
past falls more quickly than every
doubling ever you know a half every
thousand years so our interest in the
year fifteen hundred
is far more than twice as much than our
interest in the year five hundred which
interest in the year
minus 500 and so on
so that suggests that uh most interest
is concentrated near
the people who are able to do the
simulations we are mostly interested in
simulating
people like us in societies like us and
when we go back
into more stranger distant cultures we
tend to
change them to make them more like our
world like say game of thrones does
as you may know game of thrones has
characters in cities far larger than any
cities that ever existed back then
they're cities that are the size of our
cities why because
well that's the kind of cities we live
in and that's what we like to see okay
so that's my take there's the three
scenarios um
you have to pick one i've picked they
don't care
interesting i'll push back a little bit
of on interest declinings
very rapidly i know if you remember the
very best-selling
uh series clan of the cave bears a
gene errol something like that was the
author uh they're remarkably fun
and they were set as a percentage of all
our movies or
fiction i mean it's really small it may
i think they did a movie right one movie
of it i don't know
but it was a series it was three books
and one movie and so
that's really small fraction of all the
uh fiction we have
yeah but the future is a long time so
you know well maybe
of course we don't know if the future is
a long time and some of your other work
uh talks about you know the uh the great
pruning rules in the future
and maybe our future ain't that long so
that's another possibility right which
is that we may get the capability
you should notice there are almost no
stories or movies about the other
hominids who existed around and near
humans
yeah that is true that is uh that is
zero of those
yeah so hey you screenwriters out there
let's uh talk about the interaction
between homo sapiens and neanderthals
from the neanderthal perspective that
would be interesting
exactly okay so uh we don't
our our future uh descendants don't care
so let me now open it up a little bit
and again uh
as i mentioned at the beginning uh
ancestor simulations is only it's uh
one little wedge of possible uh
ways that we could be living in a
simulation you referenced one is that
uh you know that we could be actually a
simulation in a higher order universe
nothing like our current universe and
then for whatever
god knows reason literally maybe some
kid playing god on his
playstation xxx
has spun up this simulation for
entertainment purposes
research purposes educational purposes
who knows what
maybe ones that we can't even
contemplate so higher order universe
is is certainly one
and in fact the neat thing about that is
it gets rid of
some of the constraints in boston's
analysis he does a fairly good job of
convincing me at least that
yes in the future it is plausible that
we can have the computational
power to simulate brains in a jar equal
to the number of humans that currently
exist
however if you're in a higher order
universe you have some higher
possible computational capabilities
which is enough to
essentially calculate the universe
itself and simulate that
not just our brains in a jar so higher
order universe
opens up a whole whole bunch of
additional things
uh that could be going on in the
simulation it's not all fake it could
actually be
real quote unquote you know our science
really works uh
and of course another possibility is a
friend of mine
uh uh one told me about the idea and a
solomon i don't know if she coined it or
not she called it the sleazy simulation
that uh
you know even in the higher order
universe you know the you know
computation is going to be limited by
economics as you often point out think
about the economics
uh and so yeah maybe we simulate the
earth to 14 decibel points with
uh quantum mechanics but ah
maybe uh the planets around alpha
centauri are just wireframes at this
point
and they'll only bother to calculate the
stuff in fine grain form
once somebody gets out there and then
there's even crazier possible
ways to get to a simulation uh you know
we talked before
i've talked before on the show about the
really out there idea called boltzmann
brains
uh the idea that if the universe is
infinite or effectively infinite though
actually i would say
infinite and it behaves in a quantum
mechanical fashion the way we sort of
believe the universe works
then at some exceedingly low probability
brains can exist and can pop into
existence
through quantum fluctuations perhaps the
way the universe was started
that are large enough to simulate
our current visible universe the
universe from the big bang
and here's the really crazy and sick
thing about that if the universe were
truly infinite now infinite is a
powerful concept
there's an infinite number of boltzmann
brains large enough
to simulate our universe so uh
that's if that were indeed the case and
it's almost certain we live
in a simulation in a boltzmann brain
well
no so that does we have to take the
ratio so this is the key point
i'm i'm happy to guess that most likely
scenario is in fact that the universe is
infinite
uh that seems to me plausible however
then
what we are likely to be in depends on
ratios of things
in this infinity and unfortunately it's
often ambiguous how to calculate ratios
when you have infinite universes because
when you take the limits in different
directions you get different answers
and that's a fundamental theoretical
problem people have in reasoning about
probabilities in infinite universes but
we should probably set that one aside
here
and uh my best understanding is that
boltzmann brain
uh speculation is greatly diminished
when you
have a proper understanding of how
quantum mechanics is supposed to really
work
uh people have talked as if one
component of a
of a superposition was a you know
conscious thing and i don't think that's
right i think you have to sort of
focus on um you basically decohered
some parts of the quantum system
and that's why i would actually not
focus very much on the
uh boltzmann brains but i'm fine with
thinking about
what if our the real universe is
different than the universe we see
around us
i mean that's not crazy right it seems
to me
the only way to really get a handle on
that is to ask
if we could simulate universes that
weren't the universe
we live in which ones would we simulate
and why uh that is the hope is that
at some larger level of aggregation or
analysis
the existence of creatures who uh have
reasons for doing things and who compete
in some world
would be more robust than maybe the
details of the physics of the universe
they live in
and so even if the creatures who
simulate us
aren't in the same kind of physical
universe as our we are they might still
have
similar sorts of reasons for simulating
something
that seems to be sort of our best hope
for making a guess about
what sort of universe they might live in
if they
uh are simulating us and we are not in
this kind of universe that they're in
so if we were going to simulate
universes which we do sometimes say in
video games or movies that are different
from our universe
what we tend to do is we tend to pick
universes which have
similar social structures even if they
have some sort of different underlying
physical infrastructure and we also tend
to pick universes that are
less constrained there's a reason why we
love stories with magic
magic takes away in our stories at least
many of the constraints that we must
suffer under
that make our stories harder to tell so
uh
most fantasy is set in worlds which are
very different from ours in physically
perhaps but socially they're much more
like our world and
the key difference in their physical
world tends to be that
magic or something like it allows them
to do the sort of things we would want
to do
except that our physical world makes it
hard
so that suggests that if there's a
strange universe simulating us
that first their social world is
more like ours than their physical world
that is they still
have creatures who have reasons like we
do and perhaps motives like we do which
is why they simulated creatures like us
with our sorts of reasons and motives
and that our physical universe is less
constrained than theirs
they probably have to deal with a more
difficult universe
that gets in the way of their plans even
more
frustratingly those are the two
hypotheses i would offer based on
the mere fact that we postulate that
they live
in a very different universe that's
interesting we could call it
uh perhaps the argument against then
such is
as far as we know or at least those of
us who are
rank naive realists like myself
no magic no magic is a at least a check
mark
against being in a simulation because if
someone were to
have simulated it by your argument
presumably they would dialed in
uh something at least uh as you said
make was more
interesting than their own universe and
that might well look like magic
right but our universe does have some
amazing capabilities and maybe
those amazing capabilities are magic
relative to their world
no that's uh i suppose possible nothing
comes to mind anything come to mind uh
for you in that category
the quantum hilbert space is to me
pretty spectacularly
amazing what is the quantum hillbird
space
well i mean it's it's the idea that the
physical state of the universe is this
very high dimensional vector space
where uh you know the it's a there's a
linear
evolution equation in that very high
dimensional vector space which is
how all the universe in some sense in
principle can be correlated
every atom and every spin everywhere in
the entire universe in principle can be
in these very complicated
correlated states and
that's a power that we rarely see being
used but
in principle it's right there in the
math and sometimes we are able to use it
yeah we recently had seth lloyd on the
show and he talked a bit about
uh the universe is a quantum computer
that is computing itself
right then those are quantum the quantum
computer that is the universe is a
pretty amazing
technical machine okay here we here we
go
suppose the higher order universe is
strictly newtonian
and they wanted something more
interesting so they dialed in
quantum mechanics and uh general
relativity
well that would be odd because um
they're trying to to build in their own
universe computers
that they can't build in the universe
that supposedly can be built in another
universe so
that's a bit dangerous in the sense that
if you give
you know your simulated creatures powers
computing powers that you don't have
then when they try to compute things you
won't be able to compute them
you'll have to make up answers and
convince them that the fake answers are
the real answers
and that may not work well if they have
more ways to check on the answers
well let's add one more fix that okay so
it's a newtonian
meta universe but uh the speed of light
is infinite
and so therefore you can build computers
uh and there's no
uh quantum mechanical effects so there's
no limit
uh other than perhaps the plank length
at how fine grain computation can be
and uh and further because you're no
limited by the speed of light
uh computation can be arbitrarily fast
and
maybe something about heat dispersion is
different
so you don't have the overheating
problems that you have in in our
computations
so therefore they can perhaps throw
enough
classical computing at the problem to do
at least a good enough job that we can't
tell the difference to simulate quantum
computing
so we should probably address this issue
people have
that um many people imagine that if
we're in a simulation it's a very
faithful very accurate simulation and
therefore
uh if their universe doesn't have the
same computing abilities as ours or
they're limited that
there would be errors sometimes and you
might be able to tell that you were
living in a simulation
because of the errors in their
calculations
uh so some people say that therefore you
know we've looked at some sort of
you know things in our universe with
high enough accuracy that they conclude
well we couldn't be eliminated in a
simulation because uh
we would see these errors and we don't
see them
and i i think that view is basically
mistaken
uh under the presumption that you would
the only way to simulate
a universe is to simulate it in high
detail and high accuracy
i think there's a fork i think there's
an important fork here one is
do you simulate the universe or do you
simulate the agents
uh because if you simulate the agents
you can make them think that they're
right experiments are correct to 14
decibel points even when it's just a
shitty wireframe
exactly so so almost all the discussion
of simulation
is focused on agents and simulating the
agents and seeing their experiences but
if you're just focused on the agent's
experiences
they don't experience the universe and
find physical detail
they experience only some broad accurate
aggregates of what they see in here
and so it's quite possible at a much
much lower cost
to give them the impression that they're
in a consistent universe
when they're not in fact brains in a jar
is much
easier to simulate than an actual
physical universe good to 14 decimal
points i think that's
that's fair enough right so we should
just walk through though just to make
clear to people
why that's possible first of all if if
say they
create a device and it produces
error-prone noisy estimates
those don't have to be the estimates you
show their eyes or their ears
you can clean it up and present them
clean data when they see the results of
whatever experiments they run
you know they don't know that in fact it
wasn't actually run by a real experiment
in addition if you ever find out that
they've been able to put together
several different things that you didn't
anticipate
and showed a contradiction and show that
in fact it couldn't possibly be a real
world
well at that point you can pause the
simulation and reverse it
go back before they started you know
collecting the data that was
produced the contradiction and then be
more careful and make sure that doesn't
happen
so if you're running these simulations
it's quite possible
at relatively low cost to pause them
reverse them
change something and then continue on
and make sure you don't make whatever
mistake you were
worried about i like that yeah you could
have the meta universal
editor that uh maintained or it's kind
of like the consistency person
on a continuity person on a movie set
who makes sure that the flowers were red
when they reshoot the scene
uh with the vase on the table uh not
yellow and of course they're famously
continuity
failures in movies and uh there's a
whole genre of people who look for them
but yeah so imagine a continuity editor
uh for our universe that could uh back
out replace and then replay
supposed contradictions discovered by
our scientists
i want to mention that i think this
topic tends to break people
and it's one of the reasons i'm wary of
talking about it a lot or pursuing it a
lot
there are a lot of people out there
whose minds are not that stable
who can function reasonably well in
ordinary environments but
a hypothesis like the simulation
argument puts them in some sort of a
paranoid state of mind
and breaks them and that's sad
uh because in fact most likely i would
say we are not living in a simulation
and you know the adjustments you would
make for the small chance you live in a
simulation tend to be relatively minor
they're real but they're minor so mostly
i think you do okay
ignoring the hypothesis that you might
live in a simulation
and getting really obsessed with
hypothesis mostly isn't very healthy
which is sad because you know i i like
to be intellectual and explore a wide
range of
interesting topics and there are
interesting things you can learn a bit
by thinking about this topic
but it's a little dangerous
yeah i think that could be you know if
people listen to the show know when i
talk about boltzmann brains i usually
put out the
advice never never think about boltzmann
brains while tripping on acid
but so i have this book the age of m
and uh it's about this future world
where uh brain emulations are the main
dominant powers on earth and in the
universe
and in that world they have more uses
for simulations than we do
so i was able to identify ways in which
they might usefully
have simulations as part of their
regular practices
and that makes the hype simulation
hypothesis more interesting or relevant
yeah tell us about that so uh one thing
is that
you know sometimes people will have a
crisis so for example one of the reasons
we like to watch war movies or war
movies about tsunamis or things like
that is we don't experience them very
often but we'd like to be prepared for
them so
going through you know fictional
versions of them and let us sort of
mentally practice for what we would do
if a big
rare but important event happened
well emulations uh basically they can
agree
that whoever is running their brain the
infrastructure in the operating system
is running their brain is allowed to put
them in simulation sometimes
allowed to put them in crisis
simulations uh
they can do this so that you know they
can practice what to do in a crisis and
so that other people can evaluate
how well they might respond to a crisis
so
when you start to see a crisis like
maybe we've seen over the last year
as an m you'd say to yourself i might be
in a simulation here
but you would then you know buckle down
and try to
deal with the simulation well because
you know you're probably being watched
and judged on how well you'll handle
this and you're going to learn
uh later how what you might do better as
a result of the simulation and you will
not freak out so emulations
when they see big crisis situations will
be less likely to freak out they'll be
more likely to just
you know buckle down and do what they
need to do to deal with it
uh because they expect they're more
likely to be in a simulation
in those scenarios of course there's no
need in those kinds of system well maybe
let's think about that is how accurate
do those simulations have to be in
particular if you're an
m who knows you're a simulation and has
been in the simulations uh these side
simulations uh before
it only has to be sort of good enough to
be useful much like agent-based modeling
in the quantitative social sciences i
mean
if you can see clear evidence that it's
a simulation
and so can the other people in your
simulation then you've moved into the uh
trial practice mode right so as you know
in a building often you'll hear a fire
alarm go off right
the first moment you hear the fire alarm
go off you might think well this might
be a real fire
at some point somebody might say this is
a drill
but they still might ask you to continue
with the drill like
carefully march outside et cetera and
there's a point to having drills where
people know it's a drill but there's
also points in having drills where you
don't know it's a drill
so i expect they would probably because
it's relatively low cost
not tell you it's a drill they'll want
you to see what it's like if you're not
sure it's a drill
yep that's uh yeah that's interesting uh
and it's a you know a sub class of
simulation that's
less than high fidelity but to the
question about whether our universe
or what we experience subjectively is a
simulation or not
uh doesn't appear to be relevant because
at least subjectively
we appear to be living in a best we know
high fidelity universe
well that was the point of my essay on
how to live in a simulation
when people talk about living in a
simulation their mind usually defaults
to some universe-wide simulation
but my argument is that's not what you
should expect if you are living in a
simulation
most likely if you are in a simulation
it's a very small one because those are
a lot cheaper and therefore will be a
lot more numerous
most likely the simulation includes the
room you're in perhaps a few rooms
nearby
uh a few people in the few rooms nearby
you and
nothing else uh and it won't last very
long it may not last the hour
may not last the day most simulations
would be
small things like that even if it looks
like you're in a universe so of course
when you're sitting in the room you're
in
you think you're in a universe that's
all consistent with the room you're in
you think that
there are rooms next door and on and on
for hundreds of rooms
but in your simulation that's just not
true
of course you would have to have the
expense if we're going to be like
ourselves at least of simulating the
memories as well
which is uh not that high the
the amount of bits in an episodic memory
is not
huge so that's that may only uh it adds
a lot to the computational load but not
a uh prohibitive amount i've never
really thought that much about partial
brain simulations
but you know if they're possible those
that i guess would be even more common
so i usually think in terms of
simulating your entire brain and maybe
the entire brains of a few people around
you
but honestly i'll have to say well it
could be some situations where we only
need to simulate part of your brain to
find out what you do in that simulation
and the rest of your brain doesn't
actually have to be there
yeah okay i think that's uh that could
well be reasonable and if indeed memory
is the most computationally expensive
part
that could be simulated on the side in a
different way
right as soon as somebody asks what you
did last thursday then at that moment
the simulation
generates that information and pops it
in but until you ask the question it's
not there
yeah or yeah and or it could just be
like a uh you know finite state machine
right predefined
canned memories that were relatively
inexpensive to create and
who knows maybe they're developed by an
uh evolutionary algorithm
and they're running a whole bunch of
these things in parallel so in the hm
book
i noticed a number of different reasons
why you might want a simulation there's
not just one of them
and i so for example you might want to
simulate to test people's loyalty
to see if in some temptation they might
they would betray you or
stay loyal you might want to see where
ideas came from so
intellectual property of course is
important and and good institutions for
intellectual property are important so
one of the institutions might be that we
take the situation where some idea was
generated and we simulated
enough detail to figure out who to give
credit for it what were the real sources
of that innovation
idea and simulations could be
used for that purpose too and if we have
like a half dozen or more
different reasons we might want to run a
simulation then i realized
in fact what we'll want to do is run
simulations which simultaneously
achieve as many purposes as possible
you can you know test someone's loyalty
while you look at where an innovation
came from
while there's a tsunami outside you can
do a number of different things at once
and that has an advantage
of lowering computational expenses this
is just a standard
thing in experimentation literature
about how
experiments that do many factors at once
are in a sense more efficient than in
experiments that test each factor
independently
and it lowers the chance that somebody
in simulation can figure out why it's
there
yeah though uh to do uh abcd testing you
have to run a lot more trials so you
have to run the combinatorics of how
many trials you have to do to get a
valid statistical signal right but it's
still
less than the sum of doing a trials and
d files and c dials and d
trials yeah i think that's probably
correct uh
there you say there's good literature on
that but yeah yeah so there's
there is a literature on factorial
designs for experiments basically
and yes you get basically you learn more
about factors a b
c and d if you put them all together in
a single trial
uh than if you do each one separately
yeah google of course does that
right it has a couple hundred parameters
that it varies for every person nobody
sees the same google as it turns out
right so now when you're in a simulation
even if you have a
suspicion you're in a simulation you can
be much less sure about what it's for
so you can less bias your behavior to
make it look your behavior look good for
the purposes of the simulation because
there's multiple purposes
and your behavior strategy would be at
cross purposes for these different
reasons
and of course this same reasoning
doesn't just apply to
an age of m where the uh agents are
embedded in
uh you know our known universe and do
side simulations for very
various pragmatic purposes but also
apply to the other arguments from
uh you know meta universes to boltzmann
brains
right so again if whatever universe
we are actually in has a similar social
world a similar mental world more
similar at least to our social and
mental world than its physical world
then they would similarly have these
reasons to do cost-effective simulations
where they
achieve several purposes at once with
their simulation and therefore
we can be less sure what the purpose of
the simulation we're in is
especially since they might have other
purposes that are uncommon for us
let's go back a little bit to the uh the
meta-universe
uh idea and you know you talked about
some ones that argued from
all right their culture like our culture
but maybe the the simulations
for a much higher order purpose uh one
of my favorite
uh physicists who likes to speculate a
lot and even publish
uh what are frankly very fancy
speculations with some
uh discussion of possible experiments
someday
is lee smallin and he's got a very
interesting
uh hypothesis about evolutionary
universes
uh and you know the detail that he
happens to put out is that
maybe a universe is the back end of a
black hole
and that each universe that is created
at the back end of a black hole
has somewhat of random resetting of the
laws of physics relative to its
parent universe and as it turns out some
laws of physics are
more likely to produce black holes than
others and so you get this interesting
evolutionary dynamic but if you were to
actually have a universe like this
you'd have many many many and maybe it's
infinite or maybe it's a very large
number and there's a big difference
between the two
but what's let's imagine that the
simulation at the meta
meta meta universe is at that level so
essentially they're doing evolutionary
exploration
of uh universe speculation uh
through this uh lee smallin uh type
application
then we get no biases about their
culture like our culture
our psychology like their psychology
well that scenario seems to be a
scenario where
universes are just really cheap
if in fact you can set up some
generative process that a universe
creates black holes that each of which
creates more universes
obviously you're in a situation where
you know a lot of stuff can happen
very cheap compared to your initial
expenses
so in a world where computation is
extremely cheap
you can just do an extremely lot of it
and so you may well
do computation across a very wide range
of possibilities
which then of course don't have to be as
near to where you started
so yes uh in a world where they are just
using crazy
wide amounts of computation to explore a
crazy wide around to
range of possibilities uh we can say
much less
about their world from what our world
looks like yeah i think that's
a reason why i know you often use an
economic pruning rule if you assume a
meta universe with no boundaries then
the economic pruning rules are very hard
to discern
again when when things are cheap then
variety gets large uh i mean that's of
course the thing we see in our ordinary
economic world when
products are expensive there's a limited
range of them and they're
trying to be more functional the cheaper
a kind of product gets the more
variation some of them world have the
less
constraint they have by any particular
functionality or cost considerations you
can just go wild make it a wide wide
range
and that may or may not be i mean it's
entertaining but it might not be useful
well be optimistic in the sense that you
know look all those people we should
want to live in a huge universe where
there's lots and lots of creatures out
there
it's it's really scary to think that we
are the only
like intelligent life in our visible
universe and if we kill ourselves it's
all gone
i mean oh my god i want there to be a
lot more
things like us out there so that if we
kill ourselves
other things will go on and there's just
more happy creatures out there
we talked about this a lot on one of our
earlier podcasts it's interesting
uh like all good nerdy 13 year olds i
definitely
believe that solving the drake equation
said there is lots and lots of
intelligent life in the universe
but the more i've thought about it the
more i've read the less certain i am by
any means
including reading uh your own work
oh sure but but that scares
that's scary to me if we're all alone
and there's not only
nothing else in our hubble volume but
nothing else in 10 to the 20 hubble
volumes around us then stuff like us is
really really rare
and uh we could really screw it up on
the other hand uh
and i think this is important in fact it
might be the most important thing there
is
if in turns in turn if it turns out that
is true and
i'm now to the point of i can't decide
uh
maybe we're alone maybe we're not uh and
if we are alone
that gives us a tremendous
responsibility and a tremendous uh
source of purpose uh and people talk
about
the meaning crisis i say hey to me to my
mind
until proven otherwise our meaning our
purpose is to bring the universe to
light it's an
overwhelming banquet of meaning more
meaning than we can really eat
why honestly because we're not uh
i mean if you look at the world we're
not remotely taking on that task
we are not remotely as acting as if we
had such an enormous responsibility
almost everybody is very
locally focused on their own life in
their own little considerations and
indirectly it turns out favorably the
economy and society is growing
and you know we have prospects to grow a
long way but
we're not really organized and focused
on
making sure that happens um we are
stumbling along
yeah but maybe we should be i think
that's my point right but
you know if we were to stop and think
about this is why i keep saying that
the fermi paradox is the second most
important question in science
uh the first one being why is there
something not nothing
but are there others out there or not
has gigantic implications on
everything humans do and it would seem
to me
to take the precautionary principle
somewhat seriously
uh we ought to act as if we're alone
until we prove otherwise and it may be
that we prove otherwise fairly soon
right or
maybe we never prove otherwise so
ideally you'd think we just have some
scale
so coordination parameter where if we
don't need to coordinate very much we
each just do our own thing and when
coordination gets more important we
would
turn the dial up and make more personal
sacrifices in order to coordinate better
and then we would coordinate better
that would be the thing that a rational
creature would do right
well when you look at what happens to
humans when we turn that dial
really crazy scary things happen
when humans are believed that they
really strongly need to coordinate
they fight wars they create totalitarian
governments
they do lots of crazy stuff that's
pretty destructive
so that scares me i say well if we're in
a world where we really do need to
coordinate a lot and then we
tell everybody hey everybody uh stop
being so self-centered and let's focus
on coordinating because we have this
huge responsibility
and i look what what people have done in
those situations in the past i go oh my
god
maybe we'd be better off not being told
even at the cost of
a big chance of failure i don't know but
either direction is scary having this
huge responsibility and failing to meet
it and scary and
putting together the usual sorts of you
know organizations
and coordination that people have in the
past when they thought they
are dealing with really important big
things that's also scary
it's scary but it may be necessary
learning how to
actually cooperate at very large scale
uh without putting our civilization at
risk every time we do it
so that's where i would put my number
three question
along your list first question why is
there anything second is there anybody
else out there and number three
how do we coordinate i would agree
yeah how do we do we operate
cooperatively
at scale at the giga scale or the tara
scale
i say we know tentatively the answer
which is we have lots of hypotheses for
better ways to coordinate and we should
be testing them
we should be doing many small scale
trials of various ideas we have for
better ways to coordinate
and so we are failing even to do that uh
and that's the sort of thing i most want
to push people to do in the world
is to try small-scale trials of our
many innovative ideas for better ways to
coordinate yeah
interestingly that's what our game b
movement is all about uh not all about
that's one of the main things one of the
things i've been involved with for the
last nine years is
uh you know defining what some of those
better ways to operate might be
and we're finally finally getting to the
point where in 2021 we're actually going
to start trying them
and jim i will praise you as being one
of the people who maybe takes principle
zero
which is the most important thing is to
think about what the most important
thing is and then
do stuff related to what you think the
most important thing is and
the vast majority of people don't do
that
it's very rare to find people who
actually think about gee what's the most
important thing in the world and then
focus their energies on
doing that thing yeah yep it's very
tempting unfortunately we were designed
uh
or evolved i should say don't get rid of
that design word
we you know make we were evolved uh you
know to
live in hunter-gatherer groups of 150 or
less it had some loose affiliations with
maybe a thousand or two thousand people
uh and we had low energy uh source fire
being our
our most energetic source and not too
much ability to
you know meddle with the the big picture
of the universe
but all that's not true anymore so i
think the necessity for focusing on
uh on on so i've just got an error here
i said quota exceeded error you've run
out of free disk space to save a local
backup of this data
let's wrap up here just in case we're
losing what we're
getting at here uh which is uh
at the end of the day what do you think
about
uh if you had to put a metabet on in
your opinion marketplace in the meta
universe
uh do we live in a in the various kinds
of possible simulation what are your
thoughts
i still gotta put it on a few percent um
well a few percent living in the kind of
simulation where
the physical world around me is not
really what i think it is
now if we are in a universe that was
created by some purpose and you want to
call that a simulation
um i think that's much more likely i
think all bets are off on basically
where our universe came from
it could well have come from some
intelligent source produced on with some
program in mind
uh but that's the scenario where
basically the universe as we see is the
universe roughly we see
um it's just has has a purpose in the
source
but if we're saying the universe around
me is not what i think it looks like
that's all an image just to make my
brain
think it's there i've got to put that at
say no more than a few percent
yeah i i think i'm with you that i i
can't
uh even uh get any principal way to
think about
the meta universe problem uh it's just
like
above my pay grade and humanity's pay
grade at the moment
but of course it's quite interesting
that the history of humanity is
taken up with nothing much else other
than speculating about that kind of
stuff
but nonetheless we don't really have any
way to have any principled idea on why
the universe
exists or in the form that it does well
again i guess i'll push back and i'll
say look
um if you've tried for a while and you
haven't found a method you know a way to
do it then it's fine to quit
i don't think you can conclude that we
don't have any way to do it we just
haven't found one yet
yeah and it's not even obvious how we
would right
but that doesn't mean there isn't a way
it just means we've tried we're given up
now and somebody else can try if they
want
yeah exactly in terms of uh
things like boltzmann brains or other
artifacts of infinite universes i've
chosen principally on
aesthetic grounds to reject infinite
universes again
when it comes to metaphysical
speculations where there is no evidence
one way or the other
uh well i would say there is evidence in
how we do indexable reasoning but that
would take us on a whole different
conversation so there is a whole
literature on indexical probability
and lexical priors and they do suggest
in my opinion that infinite use
universes are pretty likely
we'll have to do that sometime but not
today but anyway i personally reject
infinite universes to get rid of weird
artifacts like boltzmann brains and
other
oddities because well of course many
people that rejects the simulation
argument on the same principle hey
that's weird i don't want to think about
weird universes
or the other one you know occam's razor
which we know is not a law it's just a
a heuristic which is a pretty
conservative heuristic it just says i
don't want to think about weird
yeah or yeah it's a little stronger than
that which is that uh
really complicated is probably less
com
less common than less complicated
but but the main argument is because i
don't want to think about it
but they trouble the thing about
complicated stuff i'm going to stick
with the simple thing that i can think
about more easily
and that you know it goes to your point
that uh you know it may be unhealthy
not to have some level of uh
simplification if we're gonna live one's
life right so if i'm gonna
spend all my time worrying about whether
we're inside of a boltzmann brain what
the that means i wouldn't get
anything done
absolutely all righty well any final
thoughts
it's been great talking again and i'm
gonna hope for a number five
all righty it's been fun okay bye
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com